There's something particularly sinister
that increases mortality risk more and
more drastically with each passing year
after the age of 60. But there's
something that can be done to massively
avoid this problem. I'll go ahead and
tell you the fix is exercise, but it's a
particular type of exercise that I don't
think I've discussed here before, nor is
it something that's often brought up, at
least not in the usual health spheres.
Fortunately, I had the absolute honor
and pleasure of discussing with primary
care physician Dr. Brad Stanfield and MD
PhD in biology, Dr. Jill Carvalo, who
initially brought it up in the extended
discussion that we had months back. It
actually takes me forever to turn around
these videos. So, I'd like to show you a
few clips of these doctors discussing
the topic and then I'll come in with the
graphics, the studies, data, and the
usual physionic style. So let's start by
discussing what is this major risk that
grows with each year.
And to pick up on your point about hip
fractures. So when I was um an
orthopedic resident uh in 2019, I was
actually assisting in um you know in in
fixing people's broken hips. And one of
the startling statistics at the time,
I'm not too sure if it's changed, but I
don't think it has, was that if a person
has a hip fracture, they're 50% that
they've got a 50% mortality rate over
the next one year. So basically um half
of the people that we were operating on
they would be dead within a year. And
that's a really startling statistic and
and that's why I'm particularly
interested in what um what we can do now
and also um you know to to anything that
we can do to prevent falls um you know
is is so critical for our long-term
health.
Dr. Stanfield brings up a powerful
statistic. 50% of older individuals with
hip fractures die within a year. That's
a tremendous concern. Okay. So, what can
we do?
I was just going to add uh some concrete
evidence on the on the falls because I
actually found I found a number of
studies researching for this that kind
of blew my mind because we all know
exercise is important, but the level of
evidence that I found and kind of how
striking it is, I didn't even know
existed. So for falls, there are actual
metaanalysis of randomized trials
showing that exercise reduces the number
of falls in people over 60 years old. So
resistance training and things like
balance balance training. This I think
can be more motivating because one thing
is just saying exercise is good for you
which can sound too abstract but to know
that if you're 60 or 70 and if you have
some gate issues or some balance issues
or some strength issues and to know that
by exercising you're actually going to
be reducing your chance of falling and
and breaking bones which as you
mentioned can be a gamecher in both
directions. uh that's more much more
actionable advantage there.
So, it's no surprise that exercise is
the number one way of avoiding falls
that lead to these fractures. But
there's much more to it than that as
we'll get into because not all exercise
is equally preventative. And even within
a type of exercise, only certain ones
attack the root problem as we'll get
into. Before we get to that, Dr. Carvalo
brings up two excellent points. One,
it's a bit nebulous to say exercise is
good for you. Like, duh. I think almost
everyone knows that now. But exactly how
does it impact us? That's where we get
more tangible connections between our
exercise and what it's protecting us
from. This example of avoiding falls and
bone fractures is probably the best one,
at least in an immediate sense. Two,
Jill brings up how there have been
numerous studies on exercise and the
prevention of falls. In fact, in one
meta analysis, researchers pulled
together 99 studies on the topic and
across the eligible studies, we see that
point confirmed. We have a long list of
studies on the left side and the two
comparisons on the bottom, exercise and
control. The control condition there is
the minimal exercise to no exercise. If
that teeny tiny diamond at the bottom
moves to the left, it means that there's
fall risk is reduced with exercise
compared to doing nothing, which is
exactly what we see in this analysis.
There's about a 20% reduced risk of
falls. The risk reduction is greater for
those who exercise more intensely. This
also holds true when focusing on balance
exercises. These results were further
confirmed in a later more robust
analysis by the Cochran Library here and
they calculated an almost identical risk
reduction. Okay. But in a similar vein
as saying exercise helps prevent falls
is extremely general. So where do we go
from here? Well, this is where
specificity of the exercise but also
some additional nuances related to
concept called motor unit training makes
a huge difference. Let's listen to Dr.
Stanfield bring it up. One of the things
I've become really interested in and I I
wonder Nick if you wanted to um build
upon this as well is this concept of
motor unit training. So I I've kind of
only recently discovered um this this
line of thinking where you know as we
get older that basically the the
connections from our brain to our
muscles it starts to to break down. Um,
and one of the uh one of the ways that
we can um prevent that decline from
happening is by doing so it's called one
rep max training or trying to do fast
movements. So so powerful movements and
quick movements and and and that's there
to try and stimulate all of our neurons
to activate the the muscles that we um
yeah that that that we need. And I think
that's quite a powerful concept because
there's a difference between um someone
who's older can still be quite strong,
but they can also be at high risk of
falls. And that's because if if yes, you
might be strong, you might be able to
pull something at at a slow movement,
but um if you suddenly trip, then you
need to be able to quickly activate your
muscles so that you can catch yourself
and and not fall. Um and and so that's
an area that that I've only sort of
started to scratch the surface on in
terms of this yeah concept of motor unit
training. And I just wanted to yeah see
particularly Nick if if you've sort of
come across this concept and yeah what
your initial thoughts are.
Brad brings up a great point about the
difference between strength and power
which is uh where one of these key
distinctions lies in relation to fall
risk. So yes, it's possible for a person
to be quite strong yet still experience
fall injury risk because as Dr.
Stanfield correctly brought up they
can't access that strength in the split
seconds after making a misstep like
tripping. We can see that evidenced here
directly in this study where researchers
measured the power output of muscle
across the lifespan of mice to determine
the impact aging had on power. Real
quick, power is this measure of not only
moving a resistance indicating strength,
but also how quickly that resistance is
moved. That's power. Here we can see the
diamonds corresponding to the individual
measurements with the line indicating
the line of best fit for all that data.
The vertical axis is the power output at
a set intensity or weight lifted. The
age on the bottom is
age. Uh these are mice remember. So we
aren't testing 10year-old children uh
and seeing uh massive power declines
compared to 30 year olds. uh we're
talking about 10-month-old mice versus
20 and 30month-old mice. So there's a
dissociation between age and declines in
power as the line goes down over time.
This is also confirmed in human studies
FYI. Okay. Now why does this happen and
whatever shall we do? The reason this
happens is as with many things due to
multiple reasons but let's discuss a
major one. Your muscle cells that make
up your muscle tissue are innervated,
meaning that there's a neuron, a nerve
cell that extends from your spinal cord
and hovers right above the muscle cell.
When prompted, the neuron will release
molecules that activate the muscle to
contract. This interaction of the neuron
and the muscle cell, a meioy, is called
the motor unit. Unfortunately, as we
age, that that interaction between the
neuron and the muscle cell begins to
fade as more physical distance between
the muscle cell and the neuron occurs
due to problematic molecules like
inflammatory cytoines that impair the
relationship between the two. So with
age, more lowgrade inflammation also
emanating from the muscle cell
discourages the neuron from continuing
its relationship with the muscle cell
like a bitter breakup. This is called
dennervation.
This uh unstable connection between the
neuron and the muscle cell slows or
entirely stops our ability to tell the
muscle cell to contract which if scaled
thousands of times over impacts our
dayto-day performance reducing our
muscular power. Again there's much more
to say on this topic but we should move
on to the solutions. But if you want uh
more on this topic right now,
immediately you want more like knowing
the impact the combinations of training
might have on the problem and some more
in-depth analysis on some of the
physiological processes. Check out the
extended version of this video that
you're watching. It's part of the
Physionic Insiders, my premium research
platform stacked with videos, articles,
shortened summaries, guides, protocols,
and templates, uh private podcasts, live
sessions with yours truly. and much
more. It's the steel of the century.
Well, maybe the decade
this year. Okay, just this moment, but
it's still a steal. Check it out in the
description of this video. Now, on to
the solutions. So, one logical solution
is to get a bit more specific about
one's exercise. Since we're discussing
muscle, it might make sense to
resistance train. And this is an
excellent way to go. But that isn't
enough because we have to break
resistance training into categories.
Some people want big muscles, some
people want great strength, and others
want to focus on power. And believe it
or not, while there is overlap, they're
not trained identically. For power, what
we're interested in, the training
emphasizes speed and explosion in
movement while deemphasizing the
resistance itself. That means reducing
the weight that you're lifting in the
gym and focusing on moving a lighter
weight faster. So if you can lift, let's
say 100 kg, great. But that's a measure
of strength. And while important, it's
not the objective. So you would reduce
that weight to something much lighter,
say, I don't know, 60 kg, and lift it as
quickly as possible. As I'm often
reminded by my wiser elders, explosive
and aging don't mix kindly and often
yield injury. There are ways of reducing
injury risk by using things like bands
instead of static weights or using
machines that control the range of
motion. Or if you're still bent on using
free weights, starting at even further
reduced intensity and building up. If
you'd like uh more personalized help, I
have a step-by-step template that uh
combines power and strength training
included in the Physionic Insiders as
well. Still, the point being an emphasis
on speed within physical limitations
rather than the amount of resistance
lifted or if you want less precise but
possibly more enjoyable alternative, Dr.
Stanfield mentions a great option. just
to pick up on one thing that you've
mentioned. Um so you use the example of
tennis and I actually think that tennis
is a really is a really powerful um
exercise for for a number of different
reasons. So it it's typically social,
right? Um so and so you're doing it with
someone else and it's and it's fun so
you're more likely to um to do it over
the long term but also it it's fast
movements as well.
Yeah, tennis is an excellent way to
build in these bursts of power in both
the legs and the upper body. And
importantly, as Brad mentions, if you
enjoy it, it's a way for a person to
stick to something long-term. So, what
did we learn here today? We learned,
thanks to Dr. Carvalo and Dr. Stanfield,
that the risk of fall injury is
heightened past the age of 60, and that
hospitalization from falls due to
fracture leads to massive one-year
mortality risk. We also learned that the
way to prevent that fall risk is to
target a particular brand of
neuromuscular performance called power,
where speed of movement matters more
than the resistance being moved. We can
target that power by reducing the weight
lifted and focusing on moving the weight
quickly in the gym. However, plenty of
general physical activity that includes
that power variable, like tennis, could
be a decent alternative as well. But on
top of a loss of power over time,
another factor that needs to be paid
attention to after 60 is one that I
detail in this video right here, as well
as what to do about it. I'll see you
over